Here you can see is our for loop that we looked at in one of our previous lectures.
But now we don't want to focus on this, but rather in this lecture we are going to be showing you while
loops.
Okay again.
Now a while loop is called a while loop because there is a while statement in it like that.
But this loop is a bit different and actually a little bit more advanced than the for loop, but it
is very handy in a lot of situations.
So what we're going to well, I'll write it out for you and then I'll explain it to you.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to do exactly what this for loop is doing, but except do it in
a while loop.
So these two loops should do the exact same thing, but they look completely different.
Let me actually just run this for you again.
So in case you've forgotten already what it does again, prints 0 to 5.
I'm hoping by now you know why.
So now I'm going to do a while loop.
So while loop looks like this.
While again a variable I'm going to call it J is less than a number that I wanted to go up to print
J.
Okay.
Now you think, okay, that looks simple, but now let's run it and see what happens.
So straight away you can see it's giving us this error name J is not defined.
Which might seem a bit weird because we never defined the R over here.
It just knew what I was.
But here in the while loop it doesn't know what this variable j is.
Now that's because a while loop works very differently to a for loop.
In a while loop you have to help it along a bit.
So the first thing we have to do extra for a while loop is we have to define this variable j.
So j is a number.
And whatever you define it as over here is where the loop is going to start from.
So let's say we want our loop to start from zero just like here.
This loop started from zero.
So we want our while loop to start from zero.
And this loop ended at one less than six, just like, yeah, this loop will keep on going until J is
six or greater.
Or in other words, wow, J is less than six.
Okay, so let's run this and see what happens.
Surely it's fine now.
Okay, that's not looking too good.
Uh, we're just getting a whole lot of zeros.
And what I've done here is I've actually introduced a very common, but quite an annoying and quite
a serious problem.
What I've done here is I've created something called an infinite loop.
Now I'm just going to stop this before it keeps on going and going.
Well, this is going to keep on going forever.
Basically, that's why it's an infinite loop.
In order to stop it, the easiest thing to do is just backspace this code, because we know this is
where it was all messed up.
So I'm just going to delete it and I'm going to rerun our program.
And now it's just printing this loop over here.
Okay.
It's happy hour.
Infinite loop has stopped.
But why did that happen?
So the reason that actually happened is because over here we told our our program that J is equal to
zero.
Then we said okay, cool.
While j is less than six, print j so printed j, which is zero.
Then it came around again because j is still less than six.
Okay.
Well Jason six but what is J.
It's still zero.
So it printed zero again.
Then while J is less than six, J is still zero.
And J actually never ever incremented.
Or it never it never changed from being zero.
So that's why we had an infinite loop.
And if you remember it just printed 00000.
Because unlike this for loop, we actually have to tell the while loop to make J grow or change or get
bigger, or in other words increment, which we would use in this circumstance.
So what we then have to do we want to print J.
But once our program is printed J we want j.
And this might look a little bit weird, but we want j to equal to j plus one.
So what is that saying.
Remember how I said when a program runs it first works out what's on this side, then takes whatever
is on this side and assigns it to this variable here.
So what's happening here is when the program runs, let's say J starts as zero comes here.
Yes.
There is less than six print.
That's zero.
Now zero plus one is one.
So now make this value of zero plus one which is one equal to j.
So j then becomes one.
Now j is one.
So what happens the next time.
Okay one is still less than six.
Print that one.
And now change the value of j.
So j was one.
So one plus one is two.
And now make j over here equal to two.
So basically just remember this side is first worked out by the program.
And then it is assigned to this value here.
So now hopefully our program is going to work.
Okay so what you can see is this over here is the first time it ran in this for loop over here 0 to
5.
And then here finally our while loop works.
And it's going from zero because we told it to start at zero and end at five.
Or in other words, keep on going until J is or keep on going while J is less than six.
And then again, like we had in this for loop, you can obviously change what you wanted to, well,
what you wanted to start it, what you wanted to end at.
And again also how much you wanted to increment by.
So like we had before, we had the two over here to let it go up in twos here all you do is say I want
you to add two each time instead of adding one, and it is then going to go up in twos 024 for the first
one, 024 for the second one.
And you could change this.
You can change this all around.
But basically that's what a while loop is.
So if you think about it, the logic of a for loop and the logic of a while loop is a little bit different,
because the for loop already knows exactly how much you want it to increment by when you want it to
stop, and it's just printing.
Where's a where's a while loop needs a condition.
So basically it's going to keep on printing until you've told it to stop, or until this condition J
is less than six is false.
So a while loop just keeps on going and going and going until the condition you give it here is false.
So in other words, while this is true, keep on going.
As soon as it's false, stop the loop and jump out of it.
So what's really important here is a series of a for loop is predefined as to how many times it's going
to go.
It appears that that's the same here for the while loop, but it's actually different because the while
loop is waiting for something to become true.
And we're going to show you an example where obviously this actually is very useful, where, for example,
you want someone to maybe enter something over and over and over again and you don't know how many times
they're actually going to do that.
So you can't say, I just want you to do it three times.
You want to give them as many options and times to enter something as they want until a certain condition
is true, and that's when you would use the while loop.
So in our next lesson, we will show you a great example of when you would use the while loop and why
it is such a powerful form of looping.